all right
[Music]
identifying simple strategies to prevent
or delay age-related diseases is a major
public health concern but how could you
measure the effects of such strategies
well telomere length is a reliable
Hallmark of biological aging and the
risk of developing age-related chronic
diseases for those of you who missed all
my telomere videos which date back over
a decade what is it telomere and why
does it matter how long they are
telomere comes from the Greek for an end
part of our chromosomes telomeres cap
the ends of our chromosomes like
shoelace tips to essentially keep our
DNA from fraying telomere length is
important since there's a minimum length
required but every time our cells divide
a bit of the telomere is lost and once
they get too short the cell can die
that's why telomeres are sometimes
called the molecular clock of cells
every year they get shorter and shorter
kind of like life's fuse but in some
people that fuse Burns faster than in
others
accelerated telomere shortening has been
identified as a key biomarker for
accelerated aging disease risk and
diminish longevity but there's some good
news
telomere shortening can be counteracted
by an enzyme in our cells called
telomerase telomerase can replenish the
Lost bits and elongate our telomeres so
how can we boost this enzyme too in
effect reverse cellular aging
exercise may help those with high levels
of physical activity have longer
telomeres whereas obese individuals and
smokers tend to have shorter telomeres
along with those getting inadequate
sleep but what about nutrition globally
we might expect that any antioxidant or
anti-inflammatory diet could be
protective for telomeres so we're
talking like a whole food plant-based
diet with a reduced intake of meat and
in fact swapping out animal protein in
general in favor of plant-based proteins
given that plant-based foods have
well-known antioxidants
anti-inflammatory effects there are fair
grounds to believe that the consumption
of plant-based foods can help to
counteract telomere attrition but you
don't know if it actually would
until you put it to the test Dr Dean
ornish along with the Nobel Laureate who
co-discovered the telomerase enzyme
studied the effects of comprehensive
Lifestyle Changes on telomerase activity
and telomere length using the same
plant-based diet and lifestyle program
shown to reverse the progression of
heart disease and early stage prostate
cancer and maybe even early stage
Alzheimer's and telomere length
shortened in the control group and they
aged five years as expected but didn't
just not shorten as much or hold steady
but actually lengthened in the
plant-based lifestyle group whereas in a
similar study across a similar time
frame there was no difference in
telomere length when just giving people
the more typical low-fat Dairy skinless
chicken breasts generic type healthier
dietary advice antioxidant Rich plant
foods help maintain telomere length in
contrast total unsaturated fat intake
and consumption of refined flour grains
meat meat products and soda relate to
Shorter telomeres people living more
anti-inflammatory diets tend to have
longer telomeres and the greater the
anti-inflammatory potential of the diet
over time the greater potential to
significantly slow down the rate of
telomere shortening those with the most
pro-inflammatory diets had almost twice
the risk of accelerated telomere
shortening
the most pro-inflammatory food component
is saturated fat found in meat Dairy
eggs and junk along with other
pro-inflammatory food components like
cholesterol and trans fat
Omega-3s tend to be anti-inflammatory
but when put to the test fish oil
supplements failed to have any
significant telomere effects the most
anti-inflammatory food component is
fiber and indeed if you look at dietary
fiber intake and telomere lengthena
representative sampling of thousands of
U.S adults even though nobody was eating
enough the more fiber people consumed
the longer their telomeres tended to be
since there appeared to be a straight
line increase they could do the math and
appeared that just a 10 gram increase in
fiber per thousand calories would equate
to four fewer years of biologic aging
whereas for example the consumption of
soda appeared to increase cell aging by
almost two years per Daily serving now
of course diets high in fiber and diets
with significant amounts of fruits
vegetables and whole grains go hand in
hand so fiber may just be a marker for
eating lots of whole healthy plant foods
but are there any specific plants
associated with telomere lengthening
we'll find out next
[Music]
thank you